# **FABRIZIO RUSSO**

#### **Research Postgraduate**

Ø brizio.russo@gmail.com

% briziorusso.github.io

**\** +447784695593

in fabriziorusso

## **SUMMARY**

Currently studying towards a PhD in Computer Science funded by the UKRI Centre for Doctoral Training in Safe and Trusted Artificial Intelligence (STAI CDT, 4 years program). My background is in Economics and Statistics and, as a consultant, I have led several modelling projects for financial institutions. Passionate about research and innovation, I am studying and developing techniques for explainable knowledge discovery, to the benefit of both academia and industry.

# **EDUCATION**

# PhD in Computer Science

**Imperial College London** 

- ## Full-time: Oct 2020 Oct 2024 (exp)
  - **9** UK

- Supervisor: Prof. Francesca Toni
- Topic: Causality and Argumentation for Explainable AI
- Visiting PhD Student at King's College London

#### MSc in Applied Statistics (Distinction)

University of London - Birkbeck College

• Dissertation: Macroeconomic Modelling through VAR and VEC

# Part-time: Oct 2016 - Oct 2018

**♀** UK

#### BSc in Economics of Financial Markets and Institutions (1:1)

**University of Rome - Tor Vergata** 

• Dissertation: The Tobin Tax between Theoretical Wherewithal and Practical Feasibility

Funded Exchange Program

**University of Madrid - Autonoma** 

## Full-time: Oct 2009 - Oct 2012

Italy

## Full-time: Oct 2011 - Jun 2012

**♀** Spain

UK

# **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### **Graduate Teaching Assistant**

#### **Imperial College London**

math Part-time: Oct 2021 & 2022

• Teaching support for Introduction to Machine Learning course

### Freelance Consultant Imperial College Consultants (ICON)

mar 2022 - Sep 2022

**Q** UK & USA

• Research on outlier identification and forecast for UK commercial properties index

#### **Doctoral Researcher**

math Part-time: Jan 2021 - Apr 2021

#### **Ernst & Young (in collaboration with STAI CDT)**

UK

· Research on back-door poisoning attacks identification for transformer-based Large Language Models

#### Head of Data Science

## Full-time: Feb 2018 - Sep 2020

#### **4most Europe Ltd**

**♀** UK

- Research Lead Replicate Underwriter Behaviour using Machine Learning
- Research Lead Commercial Credit Risk Scoring using Machine Learning
- Research Lead Design, prototype and build an interactive monitoring tool (Tech of the Year National Credit Awards '22)

Managing Consultant  4most Europe Ltd	∰ Full-time: Jul 2016 – Jan 2018 ♥ UK & Canada
Credit Risk Analyst General Electric Capital - UK Home Lending	∰ Full-time: May 2014 – Jun 2015 <b>♀</b> UK

# **PUBLICATIONS**

#### Conference Proceedings

- Rago, Antonio, Fabrizio Russo, Emanuele Albini, Pietro Baroni, and Francesca Toni (2021). "Forging Argumentative
  Explanations from Causal Models". In: Proceedings of the 5th Workshop on Advances in Argumentation in Artificial Intelligence
  2021 co-located with the 20th International Conference of the Italian Association for Artificial Intelligence (AIXIA 2021).
   Volume 3086. CEUR Workshop Proceedings. CEUR-WS.org.
- Russo, Fabrizio (Aug. 2023). "Argumentation for Interactive Causal Discovery". In: Proceedings of the Thirty-Second International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence, IJCAI-23. Doctoral Consortium. International Joint Conferences on Artificial Intelligence Organization, pages 7091–7092.
- Russo, Fabrizio and Francesca Toni (2023). "Causal Discovery and Knowledge Injection for Contestable Neural Networks". In: Proceedings of the 26th European Conference on Artificial Intelligence (ECAI23). Forthcoming.

#### Journal Articles

• Rago, Antonio, Fabrizio Russo, Emanuele Albini, Pietro Baroni, and Francesca Toni (2023). "Explaining Classifiers' Output with Causal Models and Argumentation". In: Journal of Applied Logics — IfCoLog Journal of Logics and their Applications, Special Issue: Advances in Argumentation in Al 10.3, pages 421–449.

# **SERVICE**

- ECAI '23 (Reviewer)
- AISTATS '23 (Top-Reviewer Award)
- BSKY at AAMAS '23 (Reviewer)
- AISTATS '22 (Reviewer)

- ICML '22 (Reviewer)
- XAI-FIN at ICAIF '22 (Workshop co-organiser)
- XAI-FIN at ICAIF '21 (Reviewer)
- XAI Seminars Series @ Imperial (Co-organiser)

### **TALKS**

## Causal Discovery and Knowledge Injection for Contestable Neural Networks **Oral Presentation** STAI Workshop @ International Conference on Logic Programming 2023 - London, UK **Argumentative Causal Discovery Invited Speaker** STAI CDT Student Seminar Series - London, UK From Credit Risk to Explainable AI Research **Invited Speaker** MSc in Fintech - Politecnico di Milano & UCL - London, UK Causal Injection into Neural Networks ₩ Nov 2021 **Oral Presentation** YAI in Finance Workshop @ ACM International Conference on AI in Finance 2021 - Virtual Event Risk Scorecards with Machine Learning ₩ Nov 2019 **Poster Presentation ♀** Joint Conference of Bank of England & King's College - London, UK